Nothing but Gratitude
We were born into this world
because our parents gave birth to us.
And we are living today
because our parents have raised us.
So, we say that our parents' grace
is like a great mountain.
So we should repay them
for this enormous grace we received.
Surprisingly, only a few people
are grateful and try to repay them.
It seems that more people
tend to blame their parents.
Blaming the parents...
For example, I hear,
"My parents fought all the time
when I was a child."
"They scolded me often."
"They didn't give me what I wanted."
In the old days, you would hear,
"They didn't send me to college."
These days, you hear,
"They didn't send me to study abroad."
"They didn't give enough financial support
when I got married."
People blame or hate their parents
for a variety of reasons.
Then, finally they would say,
"They didn't leave enough inheritance."
This is how far we've gone.
But blaming and hating parents like this
brings harm to oneself.
Because blaming and hating the parents
means that they were not good people.
Growing up under such people,
you would also become not so good people.
So, you, too, would become not so good
or insignificant people.
So, there would not be any self-esteem.
You lose self-confidence
when you hate your parents.
People who hate their parents
live their lives somewhat in despair.
because they have no self-esteem.
But are parents really to be blamed?
If you look at it objectively,
it is not so.
If they had not given birth to us,
we would not be in this world.
They are our seed, our roots,
and our foundations.
Still, what do we say
when things are not going well?
"Why did you have me?"
we retort in blame.
We ask why we were born.
Being born or dying is not up to anyone.
We can't be born because we want to
and we can't die because we want to.
We are born through causal relationships
and we die through causal relationships.
Our intentions don't make it happen.
Secondly, our parents raised us.
Nobody else but our parents raised us.
We should thank them.
But instead we blame them.
When your parents fought,
you asked them not to do that.
If they still kept fighting,
you ended up hating them
because they didn't listen to you.
That's how you feel,
but if you look at the situation closely,
even during the turmoil,
they didn't abandon you, right?
They still raised you.
Even after the divorce,
they raised you, not abandoned you.
So if you look at
the parent-child relationship that way,
there is absolutely no reason
for blaming your parents.
You don't resent strangers
who have never done anything for you.
So why do you resent your parents?
But we do blame our parents.
In spite of all the support you received,
you do not know how to be grateful.
We say they didn't do what we wanted,
or they did not do enough.
These are wrong views,
wrong attitudes, and wrong thought.
The end result is that you lose
your self esteem and you suffer.
Then should you repay them
for the enormous grace?
I am not saying
you have to go that far.
It's the responsibility and obligation
of the parents to take care of you
until you are 18 years old.
You are not in debt for that.
In the old days,
they used to call this a "debt"
but looking at it from the biological
or moral point of view, it's not a debt.
It's the responsibility of the parents,
who gave birth to a baby.
Then, you would say,
"So, I don't have to be grateful?"
As your parents fulfilled their parts,
you also need to do
your part of being grateful.
But you don't need to think
that you are indebted
and you need to repay them.
It would be nice to repay them,
but it's not necessary.
Why?
Because when you have your own children,
you will repay through them.
You repay your debt
to the parents by raising children.
But after you turn 18,
if you are still getting help
from your parents,
that is clearly a debt.
That you have to repay.
This is a debt, even
between a parent and a child.
Even if this world
may not consider this a debt,
this is a debt in life.
You would have to pay it back
even in your next life.
So, it is the responsibility of the parents
to raise their children until the age of 18.
If they neglect to do this, it's a crime.
Protecting children until the age of 18,
is the responsibility of the parents.
so you need not feel indebted.
Even if your parents had a tough time
raising you,
you don't need to regard it as a debt.
Then you ask, "Isn't that being unfilial?
No, you are not being unfilial.
This is a biological law.
It is a biological law
that a mother nurses and raises the young
until it can live independently.
Once the young outgrows the nursing stage,
it has to take care of itself.
Humans stop nursing
around 3-4 years of age.
But, with the current social standard,
age of 18 is considered an adult.
So the parents need to take care of
their children until they are 18.
But once the children turn 18,
they need to be independent.
You definitely received your parents' help
until the age of 18,
but since the parents are biologically
and ethically responsible to do so,
you don't have to repay them,
though be grateful.
I won't say you have to repay them
for their support,
but at least you should not resent them
or hate them.
Because resenting or hating your parents
not only goes against logic,
but doing so torments you.
Whether your parents fight, drink,
or get a divorce... it's their business.
Just say "Thank you" for raising you
even through all the turmoil.
So at least...
at least don't hate them.
You need not quibble over how they live.
Even if they sent you to an orphanage,
you should thank them.
You should say
"Thank you for raising me
until I was 3."
until I was 4."
Like that.
Even if they gave you up for adoption,
you should say,
"Thank you for giving birth to me."
Hating or resenting them is against logic,
against reason, and it's also a loss for you.
Unfortunately, many people in this world
hate and resent their parents
who have given them birth and raised them.
Thus, their self-esteem diminishes
or vanishes.
They say "My mom and dad
fought all the time when I was young"
"They hit me"
"They didn't provide education for me"
Parents beat their kids
to discipline them,
yet they fed the kids
even as they beat the kids.
You neighbors didn't beat you
but they didn't feed you either.
The important thing is
that they kept you alive.
Maybe they sent you to an orphanage,
but the important thing is
that they took you to the orphanage
instead of just abandoning you.
Maybe your parents were so poor and they
abandoned you in front of someone's house.
The important thing is
they were concerned for your well being
so they left you in front of a rich house
so you can be adopted.
You need to find grace in all that.
No parents want to see
their children turn out badly.
If they didn't raise you well, it was
because they were faced with hardship.
Your parents fought because
their personalities clashed.
That had nothing to do with you.
Even amidst all that they did not
get a divorce for your sake.
Or even when they got a divorce,
they still kept and raised you.
Whether they leave you an inheritance
or not...
they can do whatever they want
with their money. Don't argue.
If they send you to college, be thankful.
Even if they don't,
you still shouldn't resent them.
Why? Because after 18,
you are responsible for your own life.
If you don't realize that
and you still resent or hate your parents,
you are being foolish
and you will hurt yourself.
You don't have to be restless
and worry about your parents, though.
After 18,
you are an independent household.
Your parents are your parents
and you are you.
If you received help, you have to repay.
What you received up until 18,
you don't need to repay,
but be grateful.
There is no need for actual accounting,
but you should be thankful.
Don't complain, hate or resent them.
It leads to the denial of self-existence.
So, those of you who blame
or hate your parents,
do this prayer in the morning.
"Dear parents, Thank you!"
"Thank you for giving me life
and for raising me."
"Even as you had to fight,
or got divorced"
"Even through all the hardships
you encountered,
you still managed to raise me this far"
This is how you pray.
This is how you raise your self-esteem.
So, nothing but gratitude
towards your parents.
This means that you do not blame
or hate your parents.
I am not saying
that you need to repay them
until your last day
for the support you received
I am saying at the very least,
do not blame them, do not hate them.